<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<guidanceItem id="eb4c2562-d306-4aa0-a86c-630c5cdff1c6" Author="" Category="Authentication" Priority="2" Rule_Type="Guideline" Status="" Technology="ASP.NET 3.5" title="Restrict Authentication Cookies to HTTPS Connections" Topic="Security" phase="Implementation" xmlns="urn:microsoft:guidanceexplorer:guidanceItem">
  <content>&lt;h1&gt;What to Do&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p&gt;Use the &lt;strong&gt;requireSSL&lt;/strong&gt; attribute to restrict authentication cookies to HTTPS connections only. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;h1&gt;Why&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sending cookies out exclusively over SSL makes it much harder for an attacker to sniff the cookie values off the wire.&amp;nbsp; If an attacker can get a copy of an authentication cookie, they can potentially emulate that user, compromising their account. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;h1&gt;When&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p&gt;All systems which use authentication cookies should use SSL for those cookies if possible.&amp;nbsp; Systems which deal with any personally identifiable information or monetary transaction should use SSL in all circumstances without exception. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;h1&gt;How&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p&gt;Set the &lt;strong&gt;secure&lt;/strong&gt; property of the authentication cookie to ensure that browsers only send authentication cookies over HTTPS connections.&amp;nbsp; By using SSL, you prevent an attacker from capturing the authentication cookie to gain spoofed access to your application.&amp;nbsp; Set the &lt;strong&gt;secure&lt;/strong&gt; property by using &lt;strong&gt;requireSSL="true"&lt;/strong&gt; on the &lt;strong&gt;&amp;lt;forms&amp;gt;&lt;/strong&gt; element as shown here. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&amp;lt;forms loginUrl="Secure\Login.aspx"&lt;br&gt;        requireSSL="true" ... /&amp;gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;h1&gt;Problem Example&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p&gt;An online brokerage provides a large amount of reference content.&amp;nbsp; As this content is not specific to any user and is publicly available, it is not protected by SSL for performance reasons like the trading interface is.&amp;nbsp; However, the site is not configured to restrict authentication cookies to SSL only, so they're sent with all requests.&amp;nbsp; An attacker positions themself on the same network segment as a user (someone using the public network in an internet cafe), sniffs the user's traffic, steals their cookie, and uses it to access their accounts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h1&gt;Solution Example&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p&gt;An online brokerage provides a large amount of reference content.&amp;nbsp; As this content is not specific to any user and is publicly available, it is not protected by SSL for performance reasons like the trading interface is.&amp;nbsp; The site is&amp;nbsp;correctly configured to restrict authentication cookies to SSL only, so they're only sent with requests protected by SSL.&amp;nbsp; An attacker positions themself on the same network segment as a user (someone using the public network in an internet cafe) and sniffs the user's traffic, but because the cookies are only sent via SSL, they cannot retrieve them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;Adapted from Microsoft patterns &amp;amp; practices guidance. &lt;/p&gt;</content>
</guidanceItem>