<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<guidanceItem id="de6b92dd-e424-4a75-931e-5618c42c6aa6" Author="" Category="Server Hardening" Priority="J.D. Meier, Alex Mackman, Michael Dunner, Srinath Vasireddy, Ray Escamilla and Anandha Murukan" Rule_Type="Checklist Item" Status="" Technology=" Any" title="IIS Banner Information Is Restricted" Topic="Security" phase="Deployment" libraryId="4738d445-bc9b-456c-8b35-a35057596c16" xmlns="urn:microsoft:guidanceexplorer:guidanceItem">
  <content>
&lt;h1&gt;Applies to&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;div&gt;Web Application&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;What to Check For&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check to ensure that the IIS banner information is restricted by disabling the IP address in the content location.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;How to Fix&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Banner information can reveal software versions and other information that may help an attacker. Banner information can reveal the software you run, allowing an attacker to exploit known software vulnerabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you retrieve a static page, for example, an .htm or a .gif file, a content location header is added to the response. By default, this content header references the IP address, and not the fully qualified domain name (FQDN). This means that your internal
 IP address is unwittingly exposed. For example, the following HTTP response header shows the IP address in bold font:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;HTTP/1.1 200 OKServer: Microsoft-IIS/5.0&lt;br&gt;Content-Location: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://10.1.1.1/Default.htm"&gt;http://10.1.1.1/Default.htm&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Date: Thu, 18 Feb 1999 14:03:52 GMTContent-Type: text/html&lt;br&gt;Accept-Ranges: bytesLast-Modified: Wed, 06 Jan 1999 18:56:06 GMTE&lt;br&gt;Tag: &amp;quot;067d136a639be1:15b6&amp;quot;Content-Length: 4325&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can hide the content location returned in HTTP response headers by modifying a value in the IIS metabase to change the default behavior from exposing IP addresses, to sending the FQDN instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Additional Resources&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For more information about hiding the content location in HTTP responses, see Microsoft Knowledge Base article 218180, &amp;quot;Internet Information Server Returns IP Address in HTTP Header (Content-Location).&amp;quot;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adapted from Microsoft patterns &amp;amp; practices guidance.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</guidanceItem>